前情提要
Previously...
我发现你是一位非凡的女子  克莱尔
I find you to be the most singular woman, Claire.
我是杰米的妻子
I'm Jamie's wife.
有消息传出  拉里布洛克的领主
Word filtered out that the laird of Lallybroch
跟他的新娘回来了
had returned with his new bride.
他们是罪犯  聚敛钱财中饱私囊
They're criminals out to line their own pockets.
我们给他们钱是为了让他们保护我们
The money we pay is for protection.
英格兰军不会宽恕窝藏罪犯之人
British don't take kindly to those who harbor outlaws.
-你为什么杀了他  -他威胁我
- Why'd you kill him? - He threatened me.
很好  我一直都不喜欢那个爱尔兰混蛋
Good. I never liked the Irish bastard.
看来这个小伙子要出来了
Looks like this laddie's on his way.
该死
Bloody hell!
现在我少了一个人
Now I'm a man short.
我需要一个高大强壮
I could use a tall, strong Scotsman
剑术精湛的苏格兰人
who's swift wi' a sword.
你早点回来  不然...
Haste ye back, or else.
恭喜
Congratulations.
有人送给我母亲的
Someone gave these to my mother.
我父亲以前会拿她的仰慕者来开玩笑
My father used to tease her about her admirer.
-我们中埋伏了  -撤退
- We were ambushed. - Get back!
杰米呢
Where is Jamie?
英格兰军人带走了他
The red coats have him.
翻译：圈圈
翻译：潇湘月影
翻译：萨萨
翻译：某羽
翻译：送小孩
翻译：冰蓝
时间轴：倩倩
时间轴：小萌
校对：冰蓝
后期：冰蓝
总监：冰蓝
古战场传奇
第一季 第十四集
寻找
怎么了  夫人
Yes, ma'am?
你们马上开始挤羊奶
You'll need to start milking the goat straight away.
好的
Yes, ma'am.
再找麦克纳布婆婆要些蜂蜜
And then ask granny Macnab for some honey.
她知道是做什么的
She'll ken what it's for.
好的
Yes, ma'am.
你有什么打算  克莱尔
What's your plan, then? Claire?
克莱尔  你想干什么
Claire! What do you intend to do?
我想把我丈夫救回来
I intend to get my husband back.
你不能一个人去
Well, you canna go alone.
让我休息一会儿恢复体力
Allow me a moment to gather my strength,
我跟你一起去
and I'll accompany ya.
你这种情况哪里都不能去
You can't go anywhere in your condition.
你失去了一条腿
You're missing your leg.
我再做一条假肢
I'll fashion another one.
你胳膊受伤了  哪里都不能去
Ye're no going anywhere with a wounded arm.
那你带几个人去吧  克鲁克太太
You're taking some of the lads with you, then. Mrs. Crook?
去找邓肯  让他召集佃户
Fetch Duncan and have him gather the tenants,
要有合适武器的人
the ones with proper weapons.
马上
Right away.
-不行  谁都不能去  -克鲁克太太
- No. Nobody is going anywhere. - Mrs. Crook.
就我一个人去
Nobody but me.
我们必须做点什么
We have to do something.
我们的领主被英格兰人抓走了
Our laird is in the clutches of the English.
如果你因为救杰米而跟英格兰军队交火
If you engage with the British army to rescue Jamie,
那拉里布洛克就会遭到王室的报复
then Lallybroch could face retribution from the crown,
你的领主不会想看到那种事发生
and your laird would not want that to happen--
尤其是从他的利益出发
especially on his account.
至少让我做点什么吧
Well, at least let me make myself useful.
我告诉你地理位置
Give you a place to start.
给我拿纸笔
Fetch me a paper and ink.
我给你画一幅草图
I'll try my hand at a rough map of
告诉你我们被陷害的地点
where we were set upon.
请你快点
Please, hurry.
你想去哪里
Where on earth do you think you're going?
你刚生完孩子  你不能走
You just gave birth. You can't leave.
虽然你手上有地图
You may be armed with a map
也基本清楚这里的情况
and a fair knowledge of the area,
但这对寻找士兵是没用的
but that's worthless for tracking soldiers.
她说得对
She was right.
我基本不知道拉里布洛克附近的地形
I scarcely knew the terrain around Lallybroch.
离开这里我能幸存一时  但又能坚持多久
I could live for a time off the land, but for how long?
我很清楚如果我想
I knew full well if I had any hope
找到杰米  我就需要帮助
of finding Jamie I'd need help
如果上天不帮我的话
if not divine intervention.
克莱尔  驾
Claire? Yah!
驾
Yah!
就快追上了
We're very close.
走开  快走开
Go on, shoo. Get off.
我们的上帝
God our father,
您赐予我们生命  并引导我们
your power brings us to birth to guide our lives
最终归于尘土  阿门
and by your command, we return to dust. Amen.
我们的上帝  您赐予我们生命
God our father, your power brings us to birth.
您引导我们
Your providence guides our lives,
-最终归于尘土  阿门  -阿门
- and by your command, we return to dust. Amen. - Amen.
这一幕让我想起战争的亘古不变
I was reminded of the sad timelessness of war.
胜者把战死的人从战场运回  并埋葬他们
Victors carry their dead from fields and bury them.
败者无人在意  只能在战场上慢慢腐败化入尘土
The losers are left to slowly decay back into the soil.
我又找到踪迹了  往东
I found more tracks. East.
如伊恩所说  他们有辆马车
Just as Ian said. They have a cart.
车很重  所以应该很容易跟上
It's heavy. It should be easy enough to follow.
希望是因为有个大块头的红发苏格兰人
Hopefully, 'cause there's a rather large red-headed Scot
增加了重量
weighing it down.
我快胀死了
I'm bursting.
原来会这样流啊
I had no idea it flowed like that.
是的  婴儿吮吸会让奶上来
Oh, aye, the bairn's sucking starts the milk.
然后孩子只要大口喝就行了
Then all the child need do is swallow.
感觉好多了
Oh, feels much better.
我不能离开玛吉太久
I canna leave wee Maggie too long.
很麻烦的
It's a nuisance.
养小孩几乎都很麻烦
Everything to do with bairns is a nuisance, almost.
但是...
But still...
我还是愿意养
I'd never choose not to have them.
是啊
No, you wouldn't choose that.
你觉得我们能找到他吗
Do you think we'll find him?
必须找到
We have to.
我们要追上他们至少还得用几个小时
They're still a few hours ahead of us at the least.
他们会先我们到达威廉堡
They get to Fort William before we do,
我担心杰克·兰德尔会结束自己开始的事
I'm afraid Jack Randall might finally finish what he started.
我也一直担心这个
I've been thinking about that.
我打算避开他
I plan on avoiding him altogether
直接找托马斯勋爵
by bargaining with Lord Thomas.
他是这个地区的英格兰军指挥官
He's the commander of the British army in this area
也是兰德尔的上级
and Randall's superior.
运气好的话  他会在那儿
With any luck, he'll be there.
他为什么要跟你做交易
Why would he bargain wi' you?
我俩在布罗克顿见过  我想他很喜欢我
I believe he took a shine to me when I met him at Brockton.
据我观察
And from what I observed,
他很看不起兰德尔
he holds Randall in absolute contempt.
听着不像是计划  倒像是期望
Sounds more like a prayer than a plan.
总比毫无计划的好
Well, it's better than no plan at all.
还热乎着
Still warm.
快点
Come on!
备好马匹
Get your horses ready.
是  长官  没问题
Aye, aye, sir. No problem.
是麦奎利先生
There's Mr. Macquarrie.
杰米在哪  我找不到他
Where's Jamie? Can't see him anywhere.
士兵们很松懈
Soldiers are at ease.
只有一名守卫
One guard.
你觉得他们把他杀了吗
Do you suppose they've killed him?
他们为什么要杀他
Why would they?
因为他是固执的弗雷泽
Because he's a headstrong Fraser.
确实  可他还没蠢到
True, but he's not daft enough
一人单挑十个全副武装的士兵
to pick a fight with 10 armed soldiers.
列兵  立刻把这封信送出去
Private, take this dispatch straight away.
-他要去哪  -不知道
- Where's he going? - I don't know.
想搞清楚只有一个办法
But there's one way to find out for sure.
您没事吧  女士
You all right, madam?
我差点踩到您
I almost trampled you.
我再问一次  你们把另一个俘虏怎么样了
Again, what have you done with the other prisoner?
你这婊子怎么敢这么和我说话
I'll not let harlots talk to me that way.
立刻给我松绑
Untie me straight away.
我现在又成婊子了
A harlot am I, now?
只有婊子才会堕落到去抢劫国王的手下
Only a slut would stoop to rob a king's man.
我们不是婊子也不是贼
We are not harlots or thieves.
我们只想知道那个苏格兰人哪去了
We just want to know where the highlander is.
红头发的那个
The red headed one.
去死吧  你们两个
Go to the devil, the both of you.
别把事情复杂化
You don't have to make this more difficult.
只要回答我  我们就离开
A simple answer, and we'll be on our way.
你怕是没搞清楚自己的处境吧
I don't think you grasp the situation you're in.
她一旦决定要做什么
I won't be able to stop her
我可阻止不了她
once she sets her mind to something.
袭击国王的手下就是袭击国王本人
An assault on a king's man is an assault on the crown itself.
另一个俘虏哪去了
The other prisoner?
不
Oh, no.
不不不  不不不
No, no, no, no, no, no!
不不不
No, no, no!
天啊
Oh, god!
他在哪
Where is he?
-苏格兰人在哪  -够了
- The highlander? - Enough!
不吃点苦头他就听不懂人话
It's the only tongue the English understand.
求你了
I beseech you.
把你知道的告诉我  就可以免受折磨
Just tell us what you know and this will end.
也许烫烫睾丸能让你回心转意
Maybe if I smoke your bollocks you'll change your mind.
住  住手  求你了
H-hol--hold, please.
求求你  求求你  天啊  住手
Please! Please, lord god, hold.
我只是个信差  天啊  求你住手
I'm just a courier. Oh, lord god, please hold.
-我只是  -等等  等等
- I'm just-- - Wait, wait!
我是个信差  求你了
I'm a courier, please.
他既然是信差
If he's a courier,
也许这些信件里提到了杰米
maybe one of the dispatches will say something about Jamie.
我找到了
I found something.
你要是把信拆开...
If you break that seal...
你俩都会被绞死
You'll both hang.
信上说他们本打算把他送到比尤利郡法庭
It says they were taking him to the sherriff's court
他逃跑了
in Beauly when he escaped.
可军队还在找他
But the army is still searching for him.
没人找他
Well, nobody's searching.
峡谷里的那几个士兵要把麦奎利
Those few soldiers back in the glen were taking Macquarrie
送去比尤利郡法庭
to the Sherriff's Court in Beauly.
这封信是要求威廉堡驻军
This dispatch is calling on the garrison at Fort William
搜索杰米
to find jamie.
如果他们没收到信
And if they never read it...
他们就不知道他逃了
Then they won't know he's escaped.
他不会回拉里布洛克
He won't go back to Lallybroch.
他们第一个就会去那找人
That's the first place they'll look.
对  他会去北方
No, he'll go north...
深入高地
Deeper into the highlands.
驻军不敢深入那么远  没有补给
The garrison won't dare stray that far from supplies
也没有增援  太冒险
and reinforcements-- too chancy.
你在做什么
What are you doing?
给他治疗烧伤  包扎一下
I'm going to stop the burning and bandage his foot.
克莱尔  我们不能留他活口
Claire, we canna allow him to live.
谁说的
I don't know that.
他知道我们在找杰米
He knows we're looking for Jamie.
我们要是留他活口让他去告密
How long do you think it'd be before they turn up
不出几天就会有军队出现在拉里布洛克
in Lallybroch if we left him alive to blab?
我知道你是我哥哥的妻子
I ken ye're my brother's wife,
但我不能由着你评判我  克莱尔
but I won't be judged by you, Claire.
你说什么
Pardon?
从你眼里看得出来  你不同意我的做法
I can see in your eyes you dunna agree with my methods.
就因为我不想看他被杀吗
Just because I don't see the man murdered?
不  因为这让你困扰
No, because it bothers you,
在这儿由不得你多愁善感
and there's no room for sentiment like that here.
他不会对任何人讲了
He won't be telling his tale to anyone.
下一次...
Next time...
要掩盖好踪迹
Hide your tracks better.
我跟在后面  听到了惨叫
I followed till I heard the screams.
扎营吧
Make camp.
我去找点晚餐
I'll go find us some supper.
爱迫使人做出抉择
Love forces a person to choose.
你会去做以往从未想过的事
You do things you never imagined you could do before.
我没在评判你
I wasn't judging you.
我只知道要是穆塔夫没出现
I just know that if Murtagh hadn't turned up when he did...
我也会亲手杀了他
I would have done it myself.
最下面的木柴烧成灰以后
When the bottom log burns to ash,
它上面的一根会接着烧
the next one will take its place.
能让我们在夜间保暖
Should keep us warm till morning.
作为牛津郡来的女士
For a lady from Oxfordshire,
你对野外生存了解不少嘛
you ken your way about the wilds.
我年轻的时候
When I was young,
我叔叔教过我野外生存的技能
my uncle taught me how to survive outdoors.
我们只能依靠自然的馈赠活命
We had to take whatever the land offered.
我学会了一点有用的技巧
I picked up a few useful tips.
此言不虚
Aye, I'd say so.
你是在哪学会追踪的
Where did you learn to track like that?
小时候杰米和伊恩教过我
Jamie and Ian taught me when we were young.
他们不介意带着你这个跟屁虫吗
They didn't mind you tagging along?
他们知道如果拒绝我的话
Well, they knew if they refused,
我会拧下他们的耳朵或是在饭菜里加料
I'd either skelp their lugs or bedevil their suppers.
在饭菜里加料是怎么回事
Bedevil their suppers?
增加点调味品什么的
Added a bit of seasoning.
如果他们不教我的话
I'd show them the wee beasties
我会让他们知道我的厉害  然后告诉他们
and tell them they'd get plenty more
在最猝不及防的时刻会有更多"惊喜"
when they least expected it if they didna teach me.
我猜是伊恩让你来的吧
So, Ian sent you, I expect?
是啊  他觉得你俩需要点帮助
Aye, thought you could use the help.
但照我看来
But from what I've seen so far,
你俩可谓天生歹徒
you two are natural outlaws.
晚餐
Supper.
结账日收到的房租  你也许用得着
The rents from quarter day... you might need it.
少废话  拿着就是了
You'll take it, and none of your nonsense.
这是伊恩的刀
This...belongs to Ian.
他那还有一把
He has another one.
把它藏在丝袜顶端
Put it in the top of your stocking.
用吊袜带绑稳
Hold it with your garter.
永远别取下来  即使睡觉也不行
Never take it off, even when you sleep.
你会用刀吗
Do you ken how to use a knife?
会
Yes, I do.
穆塔夫来了以后
It was clear that with Murtagh's arrival,
珍妮就得回拉里布洛克
Jenny had to go back to Lallybroch
照顾她的小女儿
and her infant daughter.
但我感受到了作为先知的压力
However, I felt the burden of being a prophet.
珍妮  你到家后能帮我个忙吗
Jenny, I need you to do something when you get home.
种点土豆
Plant potatoes.
土豆  那玩意在苏格兰种不活
Potatoes? They're not grown in the highlands.
能种活的
They will be.
土豆能长时间储存
The crop will keep for a long time,
产量也比小麦高
and the yield is better than wheat.
好吧
Aye.
土豆种子最近只有爱丁堡有
There's none closer than Edinburgh,
但我可以派人去买
but I can send for them.
尽量多弄些来
As many as you can.
两年后会有一场严重的饥荒
There will be a famine. A bad one in two years.
若有产量低的田产和物产
Any land or property you have that's not productive,
尽快卖了换成金币
sell it now, for gold.
不久将来  将会有一场血战
A war is coming, slaughter.
苏格兰上的所有人都将遭到追杀
Men will be hunted throughout the highlands.
杰米说过你会告诉我一些事情
Jamie said you might... tell me things.
起初听起来毫无道理
Didna make much sense at the time.
但他说我该按照你说的做
But he said if you did, I was to do as you ask.
那些是眼下必须完成的重要事
Those are the important things to do for now.
上帝保佑你  克莱尔
God go with ye, Claire.
我可以放心离去  因为我知道你会
I can leave knowing ye're gonna do whatever it takes
不惜一切代价救回我哥哥
to bring my brother back.
我们是要往北走吗
Are we headed north?
是的
Aye.
能说得再具体些吗
Can you be more specific?
往北走  然后往西走
North, then west.
你给的信息有够"详尽"的
You're a wealth of information.
有什么地方是他可能会去的吗
Is there a place he might go?
不好说
There's no telling.
但他估计不便移动
But the traveling will no be easy for him,
得在白天躲藏  还不能走大路
lyin' hid during the day, stayin' off the roads.
那我们要怎么找他
Then how exactly are we supposed to find him?
我们不用去找他
We're not.
他会来找我们
The lad's gonna find us.
你是什么意思
What do you mean?
我把你其余的药物带来了
I've brought the rest of your medicines.
你得在这一带建立起自己
You need to establish a reputation
作为医生的名声
around these parts as a healer.
我们得吸引他人的注意
We need to attract attention.
很快我就明白他的意思了
I found out soon enough what he meant.
我们光明正大地沿着大道缓慢前进
We traveled openly and slowly along the main roads
在途径的每个村落农庄稍作停留
and stopped at every croft, village, and hamlet we came to.
好了  小伙子
Okay, young man.
在那  穆塔夫会迅速地调查当地人口
There, Murtagh would make a quick survey of the local populace,
把受伤患病的人集中起来
round up anyone suffering from illness or injury,
带到我这来医治
and bring them to me for treatment.
因医生在此类地区实属稀少罕见
Physicians being few and far between in these parts
他们总能吸引人们的注意
were always guaranteed to draw attention.
下来
Get off!
穆塔夫则有他自己的方法吸引他人注意
Murtagh had his own way of attracting attention.
你跳得就跟发情的母猪似的
You're like a sow in heat up there.
滚下去
Off!
你让我都想回家陪我家黄脸婆了
You made me want to go home and spend time with ma wife!
你的掌纹里有矛盾因素
These lines are contradictory.
看见这条弯曲的纹路了吗
See how this one curves?
这意味着你目前正在旅途中
That means you're going on a journey.
而且...
And...
其中穿插了一条断纹
It's crossed by a broken line,
意味着你会在此稍作停留
which means you're staying put.
还有很多陌生人
There are strangers
最近闯入了你的生活中
who've come into your life recently,
且为数不少
many of them.
如果我的解读是正确的  我敢肯定
And if I read this right, and I do,
其中一位是个身材魁梧  长相英俊的
one of them is a very tall, strapping,
红发男人
red-haired man.
你最近见过这样的男子吗
Have you seen someone like that recently?
没有
No.
我最近见过的男人只有我丈夫
Only man I've seen of late is my husband.
他是个懒惰的矮胖子
and he's short, fat, and lazy.
但你说的这个红发帅哥
But this red-haired, strapping man ye speak of...
他会带我去流浪吗
is he the one that's to take me on the journey?
有可能
Possibly.
坐下
Sit down!
你确定吗
Are you sure?
好好想想
Think.
也许你看到他经过了
Perhaps you saw him passing through here.
如果我看到过他  姑娘
If I'd seen him, lassie,
就不会坐在这儿就跟你说话了
wouldn't be sitting here talking to you.
我想也不能
Well... I suppose not.
好吧
Well...
你会过上长久而
You have a very long and happy life
幸福的一生
to look forward to.
真的吗
Really?
但你丈夫不会
But your husband doesn't.
谢谢你
Thank you.
呆子
Dimwits.
一场表演再好  如果讽刺了他们
They wouldn't appreciate a fine performance
他们也不会感激的
if it bit 'em on the backsides!
你  非得在我跳舞时给人算命吗
And you, do you have to tell fortunes during my dance?
所以你不成功倒要怪我了
So I'm to blame because you're not a success?
你分了人的心
You were a distraction.
我要担心你  就没法专心舞步
I couldn't concentrate on my steps for worrying about ye.
给人算命是你的主意
It was your idea that I tell fortunes.
我只是在执行计划
I'm just going along with the plan.
相信我  杰米会来找我们的
Trust me, Jamie will come to us.
高地上没几个能算命的医生
Very few fortune-telling healers roam the highlands
跟弗雷泽家的舞者一起游荡
with a dancing Fraser clansman in tow.
我们没别的办法来散布消息了吗
Is there no other way for us to get the word out?
消息可不会通过空气传播
Words canna travel by air.
反正目前还不行
Well, not yet, anyway.
不重要了  我聊过的人还没人见过他
Never mind. No one I spoke to has seen him.
你走运了吗
Did you have any luck?
没有
No.
这不会有效果的
This isn't going to work.
你这个态度的话是不会有
Not with that attitude it won't.
*突然  天色暗下来*
*Suddenly, the sky grew darker*
*有喧闹的噪声...*
*and there was a loud noise upon the...*
我能提个建议吗
May I make a suggestion?
或许你可以唱唱歌
Perhaps you could sing a song
让舞步更加爵士味儿
to jazz up the dance a bit.
爵士
Jazz?
就是加点料  更活泼点
To spice up, enliven.
唱歌
A song?
对  大概用这样的拍子...
Yes, something toe-tapping like...
*他是芝加哥来的著名小号手*
*He was a famous trumpet man from out Chicago way*
*他有独特的风格  别人学不来*
*he had a boogie style that no one else could play*
*他是圈子里最厉害的人*
*he was a top man at his craft*
*但他的号码被选中  得去应征*
*but then his number came up and he was gone with the draft*
*现在在军队是个晨号手*
*he's in the army now a-blowin' reveille*
*他是艺术连的迷人小号手*
*he's the boogie woogie bugle boy of company b*
怎么了
What?
曲子很好听  但你得唱点苏格兰歌
It's a bonnie tune, but you need a Scottish song.
我
Me?
还得换换装束
And a new look.
这让你欢快了不少  不是吗
That's jazzed you up a bit, eh?
我看着很可笑
I look ridiculous.
没错  是的
Aye, you do.
你从哪找来这些衣服的  都臭了
Where did you find these clothes? They absolutely reek.
这怎么能帮我们找到杰米呢
This is going to help us find Jamie how?
你催促我快点去找他
Ye nagged me to speed up the search.
一个穿得像个小伙子的英格兰女士
Well, a Sassenach lady dressed as a laddie
唱着这样的下流歌...
singing this bawdy song...
那消息会传很远的
that should spread the word.
我可没这么想过
Well, I'm sure this isn't what I had in mind.
承担彼此的负担  履行...
Bear ye one another's burdens and so fulfill the--
别引用《圣经》  不合适你
Stop quoting the Bible. It doesn't suit you.
好吧
Right.
跳段吉格舞给他们热热身
Warmed them up with a wee jig.
该死
Oh, fuck.
*这段歌要送给*
*Here's to all you lads and lasses*
*所有这样的小伙姑娘*
*that go out this way*
*带她出去玩时  一定要玉洞走一遭*
*Be sure to tip your coggie when you take her out to play*
*姑娘小伙玩亲亲*
*Lads and lasses toy a kiss*
*小伙从不觉得这是问题*
*The lads never think what they do is amiss*
*因为有肯特  基恩  还有亚伯丁*
*Because there's Kent and Keen and there's Aberdeen*
*但没什么比布基伍基河谷更湿润*
*And there's none as muckle as the strath of Bogie Wogie
*每个小伙都在想*
*For every lad'll wander*
*找到自己的姑娘*
*just to have his lass*
*如果她令他们性起  就举起酒杯*
*An when they see her pintle rise, they'll raise a glass*
*赞颂他们的小荡妇*
*an rowe about their wanton een*
*他们跳得头晕目眩  好像骑兵踏过草地*
*they dance a reel as the troopers go over the lea*
*因为有肯特  基恩  还有亚伯丁*
*Because there's Kent and Keen and there's Aberdeen*
*没什么比布基伍基河谷河水更丰沛*
*And there's none as muckle as the strath of bogie wogie*
*哒哒嘟嘟*
*A-root, a-toot*
*哒哒滴*
*A rooty-a-doot*
《英格兰人》今晚在牛津演唱
之后是剑术表演
*哒哒嘟嘟  哒哒滴*
*A-root, a-toot, a rooty-a-doot*
*他格格笑  瞧着我*
*He giggled, goggled me*
*他是个响炮*
*He was a banger*
*他想要我两腿之间的奖励*
*he sought the prize between my thighs*
*成为了刽子手*
*became a hanger*
*有肯特  基恩  还有亚伯丁*
*And there's Kent and Keen and there's Aberdeen*
*没什么比布基伍基河谷河水更丰沛*
*But there's none as muckle as the strath of bogie wogie*
如果你见到一个高大的红发男人
If you see a strapping red-headed fellow,
告诉我
let me know.
*但有肯特  基恩*
*But there's Kent and Keen*
有个红发的大个子经过这里吗
Has a big red-headed lad come through these parts?
*没什么比布基伍基河谷河水更丰沛*
*But there's none as muckle as the strathbogie wogie*
*没什么比在布基伍基河谷*
*An no there's none as muckle*
*戏水的姑娘唱的歌更多情*
*as the wanton tune of strath of Bogie*
这是我们走的第六个村子了
It's our sixth village.
你准备这样多久
How long do you plan on doing this for?
需要多久就多久
Well, as long as it takes.
杰米知道你唱得好的歌
Jamie kens the song you're singing well.
他舅舅杜格尔喝醉了唱过
His uncle Dougal used to sing it when he had too much drink.
你唱它就像在黑夜里点亮了灯塔
You singing it is like lighting a beacon on a black night.
我相信你  穆塔夫  但...
I trust you Murtagh, but--
公开质疑就是你显示信任的方式吗
And airing yer doubts is just yer way of showing that, then?
不是
No.
那么这个话题就到此为止吧
Then that'll be all on the subject?
好  我会闭嘴的
Fine, I'll keep my mouth shut.
是啊  我猜直到我们走到马旁边
Aye...Till we reach the horses I expect.
为表演施舍点吧
For the show, any alms.
来吧  为表演施舍点
Alms, alms, alms for the show.
那个笨拙的傻瓜根本没乐感
That flat-footed lummock has no feeling for the tune.
完全没有
None.
等这个乡下佬演完了
I'll see about securing a spot for you
我试试帮你搞个位置
once this clodhopper is finished.
观众似乎挺喜欢他
Crowd seems receptive enough.
现在  请欣赏
And now, I give you...
《英格兰人》
The Sassenach!
*这首歌要送给所有这样的小伙姑娘*
*Here's for every lad and lass that goes with that way*
*带她出去玩时  一定要玉洞走一遭*
*be sure you tap her coggie when you take her out to play*
*姑娘小伙玩亲亲*
*the lads and lasses toy an kiss*
*小伙从不觉得这是问题*
*the lads dare think what they do is amiss*
*因为有肯特  基恩  还有亚伯丁*
*because there's Kent and Keen and there's Aberdeen*
*但没什么比布基伍基河谷更湿润*
*but there's none as muckle as strath of Bogie Wogie*
*每个小伙都想找到自己的姑娘*
*and every lad's a wander for to have his lass*
*如果她令你性起  就举起酒杯*
*and when you see her pintle rise, you raise your glass*
*赞颂他们的小荡妇*
*an rowe about their wanton een*
这不好笑
It's no laughing matter.
一首歌不过是一首歌
A song is a song, is a song.
歌词不属于任何人
No one can claim the words.
它们就像有翅膀的鸟儿
They're like birds in the wing.
谁能关住它们  谁就拥有它们
If one can cage them, they own them.
那歌是我们的  你窃取了
It's ours. You're filching it.
你不准再唱了
You won't be using it again.
我的伙伴想说的是
What my companion is attempting to say
那首歌非常特别
is that it's... it's a very special song.
正因如此  我们才会唱那首歌
That's precisely why we chose to use it.
能暖场
Delivers the crowds.
我个人并不喜欢
Not my taste.
高地人似乎喜欢下流的语言
The highlanders seem to delight in ribald language.
而且我们加上了专业的舞者
And we added a proper dancer.
你拥有仆人
You have a servant.
显然你不缺钱
Clearly you're in no need of funds.
一位尊贵的英格兰女士
A respectable English lady
在苏格兰乡间旅行
traveling through the Scottish countryside
假装巡回艺人
posing as an itinerant performer.
不
No.
你这么做无非是出于政治或爱情
You do this for either politics or love.
不是政治
It's not politics.
明智
Wise.
跟国王扯上关系
You don't want to involve yourself
没有好处
in his majesty's affairs.
但是除了金钱以外
But love, after money,
爱情是吉普赛人心中最珍视的事
is what matters most in a Gypsy's heart.
真见鬼了
Bloody Christ.
吉普赛人从何时开始有心了
Since when do Gypsies have hearts?
没有灵魂之人还敢口出狂言
Spoken by a man who has no soul.
够了
Enough.
我在寻找我丈夫
I'm searching for my husband.
我必须唱那首歌
And I have to sing that song.
一旦我找到他  我向你保证
And once I have found him I promise you,
我永远不会再表演
I will never set foot on stage again.
向我保证  你不会再表演那首歌
Give me your word that you won't perform that song again.
我保证
You have my word.
你等于把钱丢水沟了
You might as well have dropped that money in a ditch.
他说话还没驴叫可信
His word is worth hee-haw.
非常时期需要非常手段
Desperate times call for desperate measures.
我想杰米也会这样做
I think it's what Jamie would've done.
你没仔细听  那个吉普赛人只是告诉了你
You're no listening. That Gypsy all but told you
只要能赚到钱
he'd carry on performing that song
-他就会继续表演那首歌  -我必须相信
- if it earns him money. - I have to believe
一个直视你双眼
that a man who looks you in the eye
向你保证的人会遵守诺言
and gives you his word will keep it.
吉普赛人会继续表演那首歌的
The Gypsy will keep using the song.
所以你在唱  他们也在唱
So, you'll be singing it, they'll be singing it.
杰米不知道该去找哪首歌
Jamie won't know which song to come to.
回拉里布洛克吧
Go home to Lallybroch.
我去跟踪吉普赛人
I'll track the Gypsies.
我自己行动更方便
Easier for me on my own.
那样你就不会拖累我了
You won't slow me down then.
不  他是我丈夫
No. He is my husband.
你不可能明白我的感受
You can't understand how that feels.
再说了
Besides...
我的级别比你高  不是吗
I outrank you, do I not?
-我效忠于领主  -而我是他的夫人
- I'm pledged to the laird. - And I'm his lady.
我会继续唱那首歌  直到我找到他
And I'll continue singing that song until I find him.
如果你使劲儿看  说不定能看到美洲
If ye look hard enough, you might just see the Americas.
你只剩在那里没有唱过那首该死的歌了
It's the only place you haven't sung that damn song yet.
睡不着吗
Canna sleep?
当然了
Of course not.
很好
Good.
什么意思
What does that mean?
追随你是我傻
I'm a fool for trailing after ye.
至少我知道这个
At least I ken that much.
但是你呢
But you?
你固执
Ye're stubborn
而且你一意孤行  谁的也不听
and you will not listen to anyone but your own self.
你执意要继续唱这首歌
You insisted you'd carry on singing this song.
我们依然没有找到那小子
We've still no sign of the lad.
你在责怪我造成了我们的窘境吗
Are you blaming me for our situation?
是的
I am.
这一整出闹剧都是你的计划
This whole farce was your plan.
计划没问题
And it was fine.
直到你和吉普赛人做了交易
Till your dealings with the Gypsies.
没问题吗
Fine?
这场搜索从头到尾都有问题
Nothing about this search has been fine.
也许对你来说没问题
Perhaps it has for you
因为你从没有失去过所爱之人
because you've never lost someone that you've loved.
你以为你什么都知道  对吗姑娘
You ken it all now, do you lass?
我失去过一个人
I lost someone.
在一场麦肯齐家族的集会上
At a Mackenzie gathering
那是在很多年前了
many years ago.
我的脸上那时还没有这么多风霜
My face had less weather on it then.
她是个丰满的女子
And she was a sonsie lass.
但还有一个人在追求她
But she had another suitor.
所以
So...
我想着要证明自己配得上她
I thought to prove myself worthy of her.
成为她想要的男人
Be the kind of man she'd desire.
在捕猎的时候
During the tynchal hunt...
我只用一把匕首杀死了一头受伤的野猪
I alone killed a wounded boar using just a dagger.
麦肯齐觉得这样很英勇
The Mackenzie was so impressed by the deed,
所以把野猪的獠牙给我了
he gave me the tusks.
我做成了手镯
I made them into bracelets
当做结婚礼物送给了那个姑娘
and gave them to the lass as a wedding gift.
原来是你啊
It was you?
你觉得只有你爱杰米吗
You think ye're the only one that loves Jamie?
他像是我的儿子
He's a son to me.
对不起
I'm sorry.
我忍受不了了
I can't bear it.
我们现在要怎么做
What are we going to do now?
我们要去哪里
Where do we go?
除非我们知道些什么
Until we ken otherwise,
否则回到原点  再次开始
we go back to the beginning and start again.
好吧
All right.
先做重要的事
First things first.
马儿
The horses.
需要喂食喂水
They need to be fed and watered.
大部分钱都送人了
Gave away most of our money.
我们会想出办法的
We'll manage something.
没有吗
No?
你会过上长久而幸福的一生
You will live a long and happy life.
沃德先生  我没想到会再次见到你
Mr. Ward, I didn't expect to see you again,
除非你是来算命的
unless you came to have your fortune read.
我食言了
I broke my word.
我们一直在唱你的歌  唱得很不错
We've been performing your song, and doing quite well at it.
我听说过吉普赛人不值得信赖
I had heard that Gypsies aren't trustworthy.
我希望那不是真的
I'd hoped it wasn't true.
你远道而来  不是求我
Well, I trust you haven't come all this way
赦免你的吧
looking for absolution.
没事吧  女士
Is everything all right here, lass?
没事
It's fine.
沃德先生要走了
Mr. Ward was just leaving.
我是以爱情的名义来的
I'm here in the name of love.
我们在阿赤纳森附近演唱
We were performing near Achnasheen.
一个信使留了消息
A messenger left word.
那跟我们有什么关系
And what's that got to do with us?
那个信差是来找一位唱歌的女士的
The message was for the lass playing your role.
显然是指你
Clearly, it was meant for you.
这个信使说了什么
This message, what did it say?
我可不随便泄露消息
I don't just give information away.
就算对那些有吉普赛灵魂的人
Even to those with the soul of the Gypsy.
我什么都不给你
I'll give you nothing.
你最好快点离开
Now, you better leave
免得我这位同伴决定帮帮你
before my companion here decides to lend you a hand.
你要赶紧去格伦洛万十字路
You're to go to Glen Rowan Cross with all due haste.
是杰米吗
Is it Jamie?
他知道这里
He kens the place.
我也是
So do I.
谢谢
Thank you.
一个吉普赛人对另一个的感谢
From one Gypsy to another.
杰米
Jamie!
抱歉让你失望了  女士
Sorry to disappoint you, lass.
我们还希望是...
We were hoping for--
我知道你们希望什么
I ken what you were hoping for.
我不能报我的名字让你来
I couldn't send for ye by name.
冒着被那些不同情事业的人找到我位置的风险
Risk my location being found by those unsympathetic to the cause.
现在搞起了走私啊
Smuggling now, are we?
为了查尔斯王子的幼稚造反吗
For Prince Charles nascent rebellion?
我叫你过来不是辩论政治的
I didn't send for you to debate politics.
你可以不用搜索了
You can stop your searching.
我有杰米的消息
I've news of Jamie.
他还活着
He's alive.
他在阿赤纳森被抓了
He was taken at Achnasheen.
被你的歌吸引过去的
Drawn by your song.
在拐弯的地方碰到了六个英格兰军人
Met six red coats face to face around a turn in a path.
一个认出了他
One recognized him.
他受伤了吗
Was he hurt?
他在温特沃斯监狱
He's in Wentworth prison.
三天前接受了审判  即将被处以绞刑
Stood trial three days ago. Condemned to hang.
-什么时候  -今天  明天
- When? - Today, day after.
不会很久了
Not long.
我们得赶紧
We have to hurry.
等等
Wait--wait-!
不不
No, no, no, no, no.
不  穆塔夫
No, Murtagh.
我得单独和这位女士聊聊
I need to have a word with the lady, alone.
没事的
It'll be fine.
克莱尔  我知道你很悲伤
Claire, I understand that you're grieving.
真的  很难接受杰米走了
I do. It's hard to accept that Jamie's gone.
我知道  但是
I know that. But...
你得放手
You have to let him go.
你说了他还活着
You said he was still alive.
我们肯定能做点什么
There must be something we can do.
可以的  跟我回去
There is. Come back with me.
-什么  -我会保护你
- What? - I'll protect you.
我不需要保护  我需要我丈夫
I don't need protection. I need my husband.
我能保护你  作为你丈夫
I can protect you, as your husband.
放开我
Get your hands off me.
听我说  克莱尔
Now, listen to me, Claire.
我不会这样做
I will do no such thing.
你没有廉耻吗
Have you no shame?
你侄子被宣判了死刑  在监狱里腐烂
Your nephew lies rotting in prison under a death warrant,
而你居然勾引他老婆
and you make a play for his wife?
你之前表现得可不像是个愚蠢的女人
I've never known you to act like an empty-headed woman before,
不要现在开始
so don't start now.
格列斯呢
What about Geillis?
我还以为她是你真正的灵魂伴侣
I thought she was your true soul mate.
你的不幸爱人
Your star-crossed lover.
怀着你的私生子
Carrying your forbidden child.
他俩都在火刑柱上被烧死了
Both of them... Burned at the stake.
你现在开始寻找另一个女人
Here you are looking for another woman,
她的朋友  来给你暖床
her friend, to warm your bed.
我们今天不聊格列斯
We won't talk about Geillis today.
这是你的事
This is about you.
你是个寡妇  现在不是很快也会是
You're a widow, or if not now, you soon will be.
英格兰寡妇
An English widow.
没有金钱  没有财产
With no money, no property to call your own.
不用说你会继承的弗雷泽家的一小片土地了
Save that poor Fraser land you'll inherit.
你觉得杰克·兰德尔队长还要多久
And how long do you think it'll be before Captain Jack Randall
就会去拉里布洛克敲你家的门
comes knocking at your door at Lallybroch?
弗雷泽一家会保护我  非常感谢
The Frasers will protect me, thank you very much.
跟他们保护杰米的方式一样吗
In the same way they protected Jamie?
不  只要他愿意  你就会回到他手里
No, you'll be back in his hands the minute he takes his fancy.
那些可怜的农民对此无能为力
And there's nothing that those poor farmers can do about it.
我还以为那些可怜的农民
I thought those poor farmers
要成为詹姆斯二世党军队的骨干呢
were going to be the backbone of your Jacobite army.
你这是耍小聪明  不是大智慧
You're being clever. Not wise.
唯一确保你和拉里布洛克安全的办法
The only way to keep you and Lallybroch safe
就是寻求我
is to come under my protection
麦肯齐家族战酋的保护
as war chieftain of the Clan Mackenzie.
拉里布洛克
Lallybroch?
所以是因为这个啊
So that's what this is really about?
你想控制弗雷泽家的地盘
You want to control the Fraser lands.
你一直以来都想要
That's what you've wanted all along.
所以你才告诉杰米他妹妹
That's why you kept Jamie away for years
怀了兰德尔的孩子  不让他回去
by telling him his sister bore Randall's child.
因为你希望得到一个机会
Because you were hoping for an opportunity
在他们的领主回去之前
to bring them under the Mackenzie banner
让他们加入麦肯齐家族
before the rightful laird could return.
也许是真的
All of that may be true.
但那没有改变你的位置
But it doesna alter your position.
杰米会想要你怎么做
Now, what would Jamie want you to do?
他不会想要我跟他的舅舅上床
Well, he wouldn't want me sleeping with his uncle.
听我说  听我说
Hey, listen to me. Listen to me.
他爱过你  我知道
He loved you, yes, I know that.
比我建议你俩结婚时我怀疑的还要多
More than I suspected when I proposed you wed.
他曾是个深情的人
Now, he--he was a man of deep feelings.
少用这种他死了的口吻说话
Don't you dare speak about him as if he were already dead.
随便你怎么想我  我的动机
Now, you think what you want of me, of my motives,
我的政治  甚至我的名声
or my politics, or even my honor,
但你了解杰米
but you know-- you know Jamie.
你知道他对兰德尔的感受
You know how he felt about Randall.
如果嫁给我是唯一让你
If marrying me was the only way
免遭那个混蛋侵害的方法
to keep you out of that bastard's hands,
他会让你这样做
he would tell you to do it.
看着我的眼睛  告诉我我错了
Now, look me in the eye and tell me I'm wrong.
你带了多少人
How many men are there with you?
什么
What?
多少人
How many?
十个
10.
我知道你在想什么
I know what you're thinking,
但是那么几个人
but there is no way on earth
绝对没办法强行闯进温特沃斯监狱
that so few men can force their way into Wentworth prison.
杰米在威廉堡救我的时候
Jamie led only a handful of men
也只带了几个人
when he rescued me at Fort William.
怎么了
What's the matter?
你害怕自己不如他强吗
Are you scared you're not as good as him?
我不会上你的钩  克莱尔
I'll not be baited by you, Claire.
你被爱蒙蔽了
You're blinded by love...
作着不切实际的幻想
wishing for things that can never be.
你会不会不作努力  就放弃让斯图尔特国王
Would you give up your dream of a Stewart King on the throne
登上王位
without trying?
不会  我也不会不做努力就放弃杰米
No. Well, I won't give up on Jamie without trying.
你去那里之前他就会死
He'll be dead before you get there.
那时候怎么办
And what then?
那我就嫁给你
Then I'll marry you.
如果我有机会救他
If there's a chance that I can save him,
那我必须试试
then I have to try.
但如果我失败了
But if I fail,
或者他已经死了
or if he's already dead...
我就嫁给你
I will marry you.
我不会逼迫我的手下自己去送死
I'll not force any of my men to go to their deaths.
但我也不会阻拦自己选择去的人
But I'll not stand in the way of any that choose to go.
我喜欢那小子
Look, I like the lad,
但这可是温特沃斯监狱
but it's Wentworth.
没机会的
There's nae chance.
该死的懦夫们
Bloody cowards.
我理解你们的犹豫
I understand your hesitation.
我要求你们做的事很可怕
What I'm asking is daunting.
但我知道  如果形势逆转
But I know if the situation were reversed,
杰米会去救你们每一个人
Jamie would come for every single one of you.
同样的麦肯齐血液流淌在你们所有人的血管里
The same Mackenzie blood runs through all your veins.
我去
I'll go.
小伙子  少胡说了  站到我身后来
Laddie, stop your nonsense and get back behind me.
你太稚嫩了  不知道自己在说什么
Ye're too green to ken what you're saying.
杰米在路上  在里奥克城堡
Jamie's always looked after me, protected me.
都照顾我  保护我
On the road, Leoch.
我知道如果我要被绞死了
And I ken if it was me about to meet the hangman's noose,
他也会来找我
He'd come for me...
努力救我
try to set me free.
不管你有什么要求  克莱尔女士
Whatever you call for, Mistress Claire,
我听你差遣
my life is yours to command.
谢谢  威利
Thank you, Willie.
你比他们加起来还有勇气
You have more courage than all the rest of them put together.
你让你的血统感到光荣
You honor your blood.
地狱之火啊
Oh, hell's fire.
不能让这小子一个人去
Canna let the wee scunner go alone
把所有的乐子都抢了  对吧
and have all the fun, can I, eh?
我也去
Aye, me neither.
要是出了事
You see when this goes wrong,
在英格兰军人把你的瘦脖子拧断之前
I'm killing you first for getting us involved
我第一个就杀了你  因为是你让我们参与的
even before the red coats stretch your scrawny neck.
说服他们是比较容易的部分
Now... That was the easy part.